<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly exhortation, by occasion of the late iudgement of God, shewed at Parris-garden, the thirteenth day of Ianvaris: where were assembled by estimation; aboue a thousand persons, whereof some were slaine; &amp; of that number, at the least, as is crediblie reported, the thirde person maimed and hurt.  Giuen to all estates for their instruction, concerning the keeping of the Sabbath Day. / by Iohn Field.</title>
            <author>Field, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10844.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92533</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">72799096</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 72799096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184043</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2222:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly exhortation, by occasion of the late iudgement of God, shewed at Parris-garden, the thirteenth day of Ianvaris: where were assembled by estimation; aboue a thousand persons, whereof some were slaine; &amp; of that number, at the least, as is crediblie reported, the thirde person maimed and hurt.  Giuen to all estates for their instruction, concerning the keeping of the Sabbath Day. / by Iohn Field.</title>
                  <author>Field, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-Graut, dwelling without Temple-barre, and Henry Carre in Paules Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Ianuary. 17, 1583.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device on t.p. (Mck. 227), headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B-C⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A godly exhortation, <hi>by occaſion of the late iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of God, ſhewed at <hi>Parris-garden,</hi> the thirteenth day of IANVARIE: where were aſſembled by eſtimation; aboue a thouſand perſons, whereof ſome were ſlaine; &amp; of that number, at the leaſt, as is crediblie reported, the thirde perſon maimed and hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giuen to all estates for their instruction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> the keeping of the Sabboth day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Field <hi>Miniſter of the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exodus</hi> 20. 8.</bibl> Remember the Sabboth day to keepe it holier.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exodus</hi> 31. 14.</bibl> Yee shall therfore keepe the Sabboth, for it is holy vnto you: he that defileth it, shall die the death: therefore whoſoeuer woorketh therein, shall be euen cutoff, from among his people.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>GOD IS MY HELPE. <bibl>Pſal. 7. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>GOD IS MY HELPER</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Waldegrave</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON; Printed by <hi>Robert Walde-graue,</hi> dwelling <hi>without Temple-barre, and Henry Carre</hi> in Paules Churchyard. 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> honorable, the Lorde <hi>MAIOR, OF THE CITIE OF</hi> London: &amp; to the worſhipfull, M. VVILLIAM <hi>FLEETEVVOOD, Eſquire, Sergeant at the Law, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder</hi> of the honorable Citie of London; and one of the Queenes Maieſties Iuſtices of Peace and Quorum, within her highnes ſaid Citie and Counties, of SVRRIE and MIDLESEX: and to the worshipfull Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the ſaid City, <hi>Iohn Field</hi> wisheth increaſe of grace, and conſtancie in the bleſſed truth of God to the end of their liues. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou vvill perhaps maruell (right honourable and vvorſhipfull in Chriſt) that I taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake ſomevvhat, by this late and fearefull example of Gods iudgement: do dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this pore &amp; ſuddain labor vnto you, as though it ſhould more concern you then others. I profeſſe that I do it aduiſedly, and my reaſon is, becauſe it moſt concerneth you, &amp; ſuch as are in authoritie. For vvho are more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially bounde to looke vnto the obſeruation of the lavves of God, then the magiſtrates, vvho are ſet vp as conductors and leaders of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in ſteede of God? And although you may ſay that this thing happened out of your iuriſdiction
<pb facs="tcp:184043:3"/> whereby you might ſeeme to be cleared: yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as they that reſorted, vnto this prophane ſpectacle (and vvere iuſtly puniſhed, vvith their ovvn tranſgreſſion) vvere of your citie, &amp; you did not reſtraine them being vnder your comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: this tranſgreſſion muſt needs alſo reach to you Is it not a lamentable thing, that after ſo long preaching of the Goſpell, there ſhould bee ſo gteat prophanation amongſt vs? that Theaters ſhould be full, and churches be emptier that the ſtreetes ſhould be repleniſhed, and the places of holy exerciſes, left deſtitute? I vvrite not this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie but in reſpect, and by compariſon. For I knovv that Churches (thanks be to God) are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented? But vvhat is this in reſpect of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude? VVhy ſhoulde not holy places, in reſpect of their holy exerciſes be more frequented, then theſe places of abuſe, that vndoubtedly prouoke Gods heauy diſpleaſure? For admit that the thing it ſelfe vvere a recreation, lavvfull by the vvorde of God: yet vvho vvill graunt it vpon the Lordes Sabboth? vpon that day of reſt, vvherein our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſhould be in ſpirituall and holy vvorkes. If you ſay that this thing belongeth, not vnto you: becauſe that Parris garden, is out of your iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: yet vvhy are theſe men ſuffered to bring their Beares into the citie, that thereby they may gather your company vnto them? It vvere duety in you to hinder theſe, and to take order, that none of the citie ſhould repaire vnto ſuch places: Nay further, you oughte to prouide that at the time, when by the law of the lande, all are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to reſort to publique praiers and reading
<pb facs="tcp:184043:3"/> of the vvord of God in the church, the ſame word may be alſo expounded vnto them: ſo ſhoulde you both keep the people committed to you of God vnder her maieſty, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvicked abuſes of his holy Sabboths, which prouoke his wrath againſt the Citie: and alſo procure them to be godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, to their encreaſe in all obedience to her maieſtie and to your own authority. But I would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to God your ſelues vvere not examples of this diſorder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For if there be any market, or peece of a Fayre, falling out vpon the Sabboth, or on the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdaye afore, any other tryumph, Shooting, or ſhew of actiuity to be shewed in it: you ſpare not to doe it leſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this day then vpon any other. And though preachers haue cried out, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, for the reformation of ſuch prophanation, yet there hath beene litle of no amendment at al. But I beſeech you, euen in the bovvells of Chriſt, as you haue receiued the glad tidings of your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, &amp; do make profeſſion of it: ſo learne novv at length to put it in practiſe. Be not vnprofitable hearers of the worde of God any longer, nor dull beholders of Gods iudgements, neither ſhut your eares vvhen God crieth oute by them ſo loudly, that their ſound goeth not onely throughout the land, but alſo euen throughout the vvhole vvorld, leaſt you be made alſo to feel them. God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken to vs many wais, his frowning cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath appeared by this long &amp; lingering viſitation, both here and elſevvhere: by this vnſeaſonable wether, and by this preſent iudgement, that is yet ſo green and fresh in memorie. I am ſure if you lacke anye neceſſary help and aſſiſtance, for ſo good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:184043:4"/> a vvorke, you may be, and shal be ſupported to the vttermoſt. But hither to neither the vvorde of God by the miniſtery, and voice of the preachers: the godly and noble aduiſe of their honours, the vnſpeakable benefite, &amp; comfort of youre ſelues, your Citie, and all youre vviues and children, nor the ſundry iudgementes of God following one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and threatning more to come, could yet be able to ſtirre you vp to any ſuch worthy due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this behalfe, as the Lorde no doubt requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at your haundes. VVherefore I beſeeche you in time, euen in Gods feare: conſider vvhat belongeth vnto your peace, and according to the places, wherein God hath ſet you, be vigilant and diligent for your owne good. It ſhall be no profit vnto others, the gaine ſhall be yours, many diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhall be ſtopped, manye ignoraunt &amp; erring mindes inſtructed and reclaimed; God shall bee ſerued, the prince better honored, your ſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beied, &amp; euery one ranged to keep a happy courſe towardes heauen. Novv the Lorde Ieſus eſtablish your hearts in his trueth, and giue you a ſvveete feeling and taſte of his exceeding mercye, that vvith true iudgement you maye diſcerne his iudgements, truely turning vnto him, &amp; fearing vnder his hande, that in the end you may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Fare you vvell <date>this eyghteenth of January. 1583.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your humble and bound in Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn Feild.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:4"/>
            <head>The Lord Ieſus open our hearts, and giue vs true vnderſtanding, that we may feare his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and profite vnder his hand, to tourne from our ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till faith and aſſuraunce be wrought in our heartes, of that euerlaſting kingdome, which he hath freely by his owne bloud purchaſed for vs. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no man wil deny, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe (dearelibelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Chriſte) but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the more a man hath receiued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graces and giftes of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more is he bound by duty vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his obedience. And ſurely if this bee true of all (as it is moſt certaine) then of all others, hath this little Ilande as a garden of the Lord, beene decked and garniſhed with ſundry moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and excellent gifts, whether we reſpect thoſe that are temporal or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, that the Lord might worke in vs, both dutie and thankfulneſſe. For concerning both theſe, wher ſhould I firſt begin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might reckon them all
<pb facs="tcp:184043:5"/> vp, being ſo infinite both in the one &amp; in the other. And firſt concerning tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall giftes, what is it, that in his rich mercy, either for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuſtentation &amp; maintenance of this life, or for other earthly commodities and pleaſures, that he hath not beſtowed vppon vs? he hath ſet vs, as it were in the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of the world: where euen within our ſelues wee haue all good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things: he hath giuen vs the fat of the earth, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dew of heauen: he hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth fruitfull vnder vs, &amp; the heauens beneficial aboue vs: we haue corne, wooll, fleſh, &amp; fiſh in great plenty, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, &amp; the fouls of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire are ours: we haue gold, ſiluer Copper, Tinne, Lead and Yron, with other commodious mettals in al plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Againe, with theſe earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and al the reſt, he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs publique peace, protection &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes. Euery man enioyeth his wife, Children, goods, Cattell, and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſitteth vnder his own Vine, and heareth the voyce of his children in the ſtreetes. Our young
<pb facs="tcp:184043:5"/> men and our maidens, reioice in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique places, and the noyſe of Muſick is heard in our aſſemblies. We drink in Bowles of golde, and in cuppes of ſiluer: our heads are annoynted with ſweete ointmentes, and our faces are cheereful, becauſe our harts are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Our Princes ſit in the gates, and our Nobilitie ride in Charriots and Coches. The voyce of mourning is not heard amongeſt vs, neither hath terrour and fear amazed vs. Our wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons are turned into Plowe Shares, and Lions and Lambs do play toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without hurting one another.</p>
            <p>As for ſpirituall thinges beſtowed vpon vs, they are infinite: how ſhould I giue but a ſhadowe of them? God hath giuen himſelfe vnto vs to be our God, and hath choſen vs to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. He hath giuen vnto vs his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, and with him, all other good things, neceſſary for our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: he hath giuen him to vs, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to take our nature vppon him, to die for our ſinnes, &amp; to vndergo euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting damnation, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end he might
<pb facs="tcp:184043:6"/> acquite &amp; deliuer vs. For this he fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, wraſtled hand to hand with his fathers iudgements, was caſt, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned, and crucified, &amp; as a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected of God, and thrown down into the extreameſt humiliation, became the moſt forelorne of the worlde, that he might recouer happineſſe for vs. And therfore he aduanced his power, and brake the chaynes of death and of hell, aſcended with glory, making a ſhew of all his enemies, and giuing giftes vnto men. For all this hee wrought for vs, and for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we might be a peculier peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto himſelfe: vppon whome he would powre forth the whole riches of his mercy. And in déede vppon his Church what is there, that he might haue more done for her, that hee hath not done. Hee hath purged her by his own bloud out of her bloud, and crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned her with his righteouſneſſe. Hee hath giuen her a place in the higheſt heauens, and ſtrengthened her to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer all her enemies. He hath forgiuen her her ſinnes, and decked
<pb facs="tcp:184043:6"/> her with ſpeciall ioy, and peace that paſſeth all vnderſtanding: he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen her the goſpell, a tydings of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, wherein the riches of his grace are fully diſplaied. Can the heart of man conceiue, the tong vtter, or the pen ſet downe, what God hath done for his people in all times and ages? he did much for his people in <hi>Egypt</hi> land: but hee hath done more for vs. He did much for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being in wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but he hath done more for vs. He did much for them when hee made ſo many kings to fal before them, when he brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the land of promiſe: but he hath done more for vs: he hath euercome a mightier army, and made greater Kings to bow vnder his ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and brought vs to a larger inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which can neither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wither nor periſh. He fed them with <hi>Manna,</hi> that corrupted, when they tranſgreſſed the commandment touching the ſabboth: but he hath fed vs with him ſelf, that our corruption might be put off, and we might be clad with immortallity and euerlaſting glorye. The Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:184043:7"/> were his people, by a conditionall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, that ſtoode in their obedience: they were the apple of his eye, and ſignet of his ſcale, to whome he gaue peculier bleſſinges: and yet becauſe they were vnthankful, and knew not the day of their viſitation, they haue no part by reaſon of their vnbeliefe, in the promiſes that were made to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and the reſt of the Patriarks, to their ſéede and poſteritie: but wee are his people adopted, aſſured in a new couenant, ſealed in the blood and obedience of Ieſus Chriſte, the end of all the promiſes: whoſe ſaluation is nowe wrought and perfourmed, if hee be in vs &amp; we in him; if his glorious grace and mercy haue not appeared in vaine vnto vs. What could the Lord haue done more for his people then he did for them, &amp; yet <hi>Iſay</hi> the Prophet vpbraided them for their ingratitude, ſo many excellent bene fits of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſtowed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>I wyl ſing to my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 5.</note> 
               <hi>beloued a ſong of my beloued of his vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. My beloued had a vineyeard in a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry fruitful hil, he hedged it about, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:184043:7"/> out the stones of it, he planted it with the best plants, &amp; buylt a Tower in the mydest of it, &amp; made a winepres in it. He looked that it ſhold haue broght forth grapes, but it brought forth wyld grapes. O Inhabitants of Ieruſalem, &amp; men of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iudge therefore, between me &amp; my vineyard. What could I haue done more to my vineyard, that I haue not done vnto it? Why haue I looked that it shuld bring forth grapes, and it bryngeth forth wylde Grapes? Now I wyll tell you, what I wyll do to my Vyneyard, I wyll take away the hedge therof, &amp; it shalbe eaten vp, I wyll break downe the Wall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it shalbe tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote. And I wyll lay it waste, it shall not be cut nor digged, but Bryars and thornes shal grow vp: I wyl alſo com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mand the clouds that they rayne no rayne vppon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee how the Prophet ſetteth forth the large liberalitie and goodneſſe of God towards his people: and againe their vnthankfulnes, with thoſe iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments that it drewe vpon them: The benefits no doubt that God had beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppon them were excellent, but
<pb facs="tcp:184043:8"/> their abuſe was like wiſe intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and therefore for the one, there is threatned the taking of them away, and for the other, what horrible pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments he would bring vpon, them He taketh his occaſion, from a plaine parable, becauſe it ſhold be vnderſtod: leaning down to their capacitie, euen as our ſauiour Chriſt did in his docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and inſtructions. And yet I ſuppoſe he coulde haue ſoared as high in the clouds as any other. So <hi>Paule</hi> vſed ſimilitudes taken from huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, from building, from running<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 18. 19. Ioh. 15. 14.</note> and from fighting and ſuch like. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in a plaine ſtile applieth himſelfe to the capacitie of the rude people, in the higheſt hiſtorie that euer was written, concerning the creation of the world. This is againſte his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, his ſpouſe and Church, euen to his beloued the ſpouſes friend.</p>
            <p>The ſituation of this vineyarde was in an open and fruitful place: It had a notable Tower in it, to defend it, it had a hedge round about it, and a wyne preſſe in it. Theſe were rare
<pb facs="tcp:184043:8"/> and excellent benefites, and yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of grapes, it brought forth wilde grapes. The like in euery reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with vs. Hee hath giuen vs a lot in a pleaſant and good place, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he might haue ſet vs in one more barren. He hath in mercy planted his vineyeard amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, hedged it about and built a Tower of defence, and a wine preſſe in it, to gather the fruite of it: this was not done by our owne arme, nor by our owne election, but in his good mercy: And as he waited for fruit, in great patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were executed, ſo he hath way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon vs theſe many yeares: he ſits looking to that tree mentioned in the Goſpell, which long ſince had beene plucked vp by the rootes, had nothe in a wonderful patience expected our conuerſion and better fruites. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacke it was ill with them, it is worſe with vs, they brought foorth wylde grapes, but ours are ſcarce grapes. They were taxed with many ſinnes, but ours are multiplied as the ſande of the ſea, and as the drops of heauen.
<pb facs="tcp:184043:9"/> We are come to the dotage of the world, ſet on miſchiefe, and growing to worſe and worſe iniquity, as our Sauiour ſaith is multiplied, and the nearer he hath approched vnto vs, the faſter and further of doth the worlde flye from him. It is ſo laden with ſins and abhominations, that greuous is ſhipwracke, when a ſhip is lefte to the winds to be toſſed, and without a guyde, it muſt needes be drowned. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, muſte this tottering worlde come to vtter deſtruction. Onely they ſhall be preſerued that walke with God, to beleeue his promiſes, and to feare his iudgements: They ſhall be preſerued that are his, of all tymes: whome he hath loued, choſen, called, iuſtified, ſanctified and ſaued, in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his ſonne. Theſe ſhall not abuſe his patience, but tremble at his iudgements, and be carefull to walke in all dutifull obedience. They ſhall make haſt to meete him, when fire is come foorth from him, but the wicked ſhall ſcorne his wonderfull and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull long ſufferaunce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to their owne
<pb facs="tcp:184043:9"/> deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Becauſe hee cutteth not downe the trée at once, being ſtaid by the praiers and humiliations of his ſeruantes: that in contrite harts how downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: the wicked inſulte and are more incouraged, and as it were fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in their ſinnes and wickedneſſe, euen to diſpite him, (as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and other tyrants did) vpon whom yet he<note place="margin">Exod 5. &amp;c. Exod. 17. Num. 21. 31.</note> brought a ſwifte and a ſudden deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And yet the greateſt Okes are cut down with a little blaſt from him &amp; the higheſt buildings can not ſtand if hee doe but ſhake them. For he is iuſt, euen as he is mercifull, and hee loueth iuſtice to puniſh the wicked, &amp;<note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to mayntain the godly. If the thrones of earthly princes, muſt ſtand vppon theſe pillers, no doubt the throne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is Iudge of the whol world muſt be founded thereon, that as the Prophet ſayth. <hi>He may doe Iustice, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9.</note> 
               <hi>shewe mercy and iudgement vppon the earth.</hi> So he made <hi>Amalecke</hi> an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his wrathe, <hi>Canaen</hi> the king of <hi>Arad, Sehon</hi> of the <hi>Amor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>its:</hi> and <hi>Ogg</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184043:10"/> of <hi>Baſan,</hi> So he met with <hi>Eglon</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 3. Iudg. 4.</note> ſlaine by the hande of <hi>Aod,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with the army of <hi>Iabine</hi> king of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> that had oppreſſed <hi>Iſraell</hi> by the<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.</note> ſpace of twenty yeeres. <hi>Gedeon</hi> was his hand againſt the <hi>Madianit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and though <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeb</hi> fled awaye, yet they were afterwardes taken and killed.</p>
            <p>The Princes of the <hi>Phylistims</hi> though they were many and mightie, and thought themſelues in ſafety and aſſurance in their Temple of <hi>Dagon:</hi> yet his hand founde them out, and in mocking of <hi>Sampſon:</hi> they laſtly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a iuſt iudgemente méete for their iniquity. what ſhould I ſpeak of <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 17. 2. Sam. 15. 17</note> and <hi>Agag,</hi> of huge <hi>Goliah,</hi> of <hi>Achab,</hi> of <hi>Hazael,</hi> of <hi>Senacharib,</hi> of <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> of <hi>Antiochus, Herod</hi> &amp; al the like: becauſe<note place="margin">1. King. 20.</note> they were cruell, were they exempt<note place="margin">2. Kin. 6. 7. 8.</note> from iudgementes? No no, he found them out, and he will finde out all his enemies. He will ſtrike them vppon the hearie ſcalpes, and their cheeke bones ſhall be broken, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe their backes, and his iudgements ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:184043:10"/> declare his iuſtice, from generation to generation. The liues of the wicked are not in their owne hands, but the Godly are the cauſe of their proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Theſe from whom they ſeeke to take l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, goodes, and limmes, are in cauſe, that they are ſpared for a time in the world. And hereby as God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his to repentance, ſo he hardneth the Godles in their ſinnes, that hee may be glorified in his iuſte iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. But where are the wyſe to marke theſe thinges, and to make their profit? Who taketh a note of his iudgementes ſhewed againſt our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, that we might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to repentance? Our benefits haue beene greater, then euer were beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon any Nation excepting one or other: and do we walke worthy of them? Is there thankfulneſſe in vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to retourne vnto him the praiſe of his mercies. He hath giuen vnto vs his worde, which is an incomparable iewell, in reſpect of which the pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mograph ſayth: He hath not delt ſo with euery nation: but doe we bring
<pb facs="tcp:184043:11"/> foorth the fruits of it. Nay doe we not rather treade it vnder our feete, as it were in diſpite of the author of it? Is it not a lanterne vnto our feete, with out which, we muſt ſtray? And is it not the food of the ſoule, with out which we muſt ſtarue: and yet who doth either ſeeke vnto it, or feele the ſweet comfort of it? If the prophet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the inhabitauntes of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and to the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> to iudge this cauſe, being come to an iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, in the aſſurance of it, committing it euen to them ſelues: ſhall not our owne mouthes, in the teſtimonie of our conſcience pronounce ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs? who ſeeke his grace to late, and ſtay vntill his irreuocable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is paſſed? He that hath eares to heare let him heare, while God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto vs. He that might haue been both iudge and accuſer, wil haue vs both to iudge and accuſe our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that we may vnderſtande, how greatly we haue diſpleaſed him. And if our conſcience pronounce againſte vs, is not God greater then our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?
<pb facs="tcp:184043:11"/> If our owne heart condemne vs, is not God greater then our heart? We are wont to be partiall in our owne cauſes, becauſe our ſenſes are dull to perceiue our own iniquities: and yet he committeth this to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to the ende to drawe vs to ſpeedy repentance.</p>
            <p>True it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our partialities, though we would flatter our ſelues, &amp; could be ſo impudent to do it, that cannot ſtain his iudgementes, but euen as he tooke away the hedge of his vineyard, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing him ſelfe a iuſt iudge, in being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged vpon their vnthankfulnes, ſo he will deale with vs. That which he hath builded amongſt vs, he wil ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw againe. That which he hath compaſſed about from forrein force, from oppreſſion of enemies, to keepe out vncleane beaſtes, that he might haue receiued a large croppe, he will lay open and waſte. The wall and tower, ſhall be ouertourned within, beaſtes, dogges and hogges without ſhall fall vpon it, deuour and trample it vnder their feete. One ſtone ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:184043:12"/> bruiſe another, &amp; the cloudes ſhall not raine, to make it fruitful but to make it ranck w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thorns &amp; briers. O <hi>England</hi> repent, thou that haſt taſted of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſinges, and yet haſt prouoked God with ſo many ſinnes. O <hi>London</hi> repent, thou that haſte ſit as a Lady &amp; Queen ouer thy neighbour Cities, to whom the Lord hath giuen beſides temporall bleſſinges theſe precious iewels: ſending thee many meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to warne thee, to preach vnto thee, and to comfort thee: but thou haſt not regarded the day of thy viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If thy hedge be taken awaye, if thou be laide open and waſte for thy horrible ſinnes. If the Lord plant his vineyeard in an other place, a more fruitful ſoyle: what ſhall be come of thee? Is God more bound vnto thee, then he was vnto his owne people? Haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> any greater priuiledge, then they who were once ſo precious in his ſight? And if he ſpared not them, will he ſpare thee, that doeſt paſſe them in all abhominations? they regarded not the holy commandementes of God, to
<pb facs="tcp:184043:12"/> keep them and obſerue them, no more doeſt thou. They were Idolaters and followed the Gods of the Nations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one rearing vp an Idoll in his owne heart, and following his owne will, and ſo doeſt thou: thou art as far from the true ſpirituall worſhippe of God, belonging to ſuche a maieſtie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they were. His precious name is prophaned &amp; abuſed euery where, in ſwearing, forſwearing, and lying, thinking, ſpeaking, and practiſing ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly &amp; wickedly of it. And as for the Lordes Sabboth, as in times paſt they did defile it, did not conſecrat it to God, to reſte from ſinne and to followe his will, but gaue him onely a ceremonial &amp; outward ſeruice, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with following their owne willes, euen ſo doſt thou. This day is the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both of the Lorde thy God: that is to ſay: a daye conſecrated to his glorye, wherein, all ſolemne aſſemblies of Gods ſayntes ſhoulde bee occupied in hearing his worde, in giuing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to prayer, in receiuing his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, in meditating of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb facs="tcp:184043:13"/> workes, and putting in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of holy duties: but we contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, euen from the higheſt to the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, break this Sabboth of the Lord our God, whither we come or do not come to the place appointed: For if we come, wee come with prophane minds, deuided from God, for cuſtom and faſhions ſake, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for ſo ſpirituall a ſeruice, there hearing we heare not, to make any conſcience to learne our duties to grow in knowledge and carefully to practiſe holy doctrines: wee come as they did in the Prophets times, with lame ſacrifices, hauing ſerued firſt our ſelues, &amp; as they did in their ſolemne faſts: We bowe down our heads like Bull ruſhes, and perhaps haue torn garmentes, wee put on the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of ſorrowe, and our faces are not annointed: but there is in vs no ſorrow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leadeth to repentaunce, nor hearty turning vnto our God. Wee come to ſit before the miniſters, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people then did before the prophets, to heare the word preached, as ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt
<pb facs="tcp:184043:13"/> ſong: but when they haue ſayde they haue done: we go our wayes, and they paſſe through our iudgementes, but the worde is paſſed as a dreame. And if theſe ſinns be found, in al ſorts of our commers, what ſhall we think of them that come not at all, who through couetouſnes and prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſpiſe theſe holy aſſemblies: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther following their wordly chaffaire and buſines, or elſe thinking that the ſabboth is well ynough kept, if they giue God ſome little peece thereof, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſome i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they bee idle, following their pleaſures, and wicked paſtimes with al gréedines. O Lord what ſhall become of theſe looſe and ſinnful dais? Howe manye prophane perſons are there in this realme, both in City and Country, that hauing taken a muſter of all the holidays in the yeare, vrge the keeping of them, and wil looſe no iot of tune, that they may follow their vayn delights, and yet know not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how to keepe one holy or Sabboth day to the prayſe and honour of God? Both in Sommer and Winter, they
<pb facs="tcp:184043:14"/> can finde occaſions, to bereaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of ſpirituall comfortes, eyther to runne out into the countrie with their bagges and bottels, or els bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home to follow wicked exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. Euery dore hath his ſtake, and the ſtreetes are full of blazers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. There is gadding to al kind of gaming, and there is no Tauerne or Alehouſe, if the drinke be ſtrong, that lacketh anye company: There is no dycing houſe, bowling alley, or The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater, that can be found emptie. Thoſe flagges of defiaunce againſt God, and trumpets that are blowne to gather ſuch company, will ſooner preuaile to fill thoſe places, then the preaching of the holy worde of God, the Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and inſtructing of Children and Seruauntes, canne be to fill Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>Nothing can ſtoppe them from the ſame: neyther feare of daunger, loſſe of tyme, corruption of maners, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of diſeaſes, expence of money, ſuſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of honeſtie and ſuche like. But to the other, where to they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:184043:14"/> come with great ioye and cheerefully, as to the houſe of the Lord, nothing in a maner can allure or draw them, neyther theire owne neceſſitie, the ſweetnes and comforte of true doctrine, the reformation of maners, the holyneſſe and obedience that by the grace of God, is wrought in his Children, by ſuch exerciſes: nor the hope and aſſuraunce it ſelfe of fayth and ſaluation. Here three pence, ſixe pence, a ſhilling or two a quarter, is a great matter and a wonderfull bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, much humming and hawing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, but poundes and hundreds can be well ynough afforded, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing theſe leaſt pleſures, euery dore hath a payment, and euery Gallerie maketh a yearely ſtipend. Euery dog hath a coller, &amp; euery Beare a priſe.</p>
            <p>Here is no feare of infection, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie inconuenience or diſcommoditie that can let them. Is not this thinke you to keepe the Sabboth? the lawes of the land haue Godly prouided, that all the people of all ſortes, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre to the publique places of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:184043:15"/> worſhip, then to be taught and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted in the wholeſome word of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and there is a penaltie ſet vpon it: but how this is looked vnto tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout the lande, I leaue it to them to conſider that are wyſe and in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. The Lorde bleſſed the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daye, and ſanctified it, becauſe in it hee reſted from all the workes of his hande, that hereby we might learne, to reſt from ſinne and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and conſecrate our ſelues to his ſpiritual ſeruice. And this he inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for mans commoditie, that al fleſh might come to worſhippe before his face: He gaue them double food in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of this, that it might abide with them, and that none might come out of their place, but might reſt in his prouiſion and prouidence: So that it appeareth, he woulde not haue them occupied in making prouiſion for the bellie, to gather ſtickes, to treade the preſſe, or to carry burthens, either vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their owne ſhoulders, or vppon their beaſtes The commaundement for the obſeruing of it, is ſo often ſet
<pb facs="tcp:184043:15"/> downe in the ſcripture, as nothing more. <hi>The ſeuenth day is the Sabboth of the Lord thy God: Thou shalt do no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worke in it, neither thou, nor thy Sonne or Daughter, thy man ſeruannt or thy mayde, thy Cattle and the straunger that is within thy gates. Keepe my ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, for it is holy vnto you: He that shall defile it, shall dye the death: He that shall worke on that daye, his ſoule shall be cut off, from the middest of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe <hi>to worke,</hi> is to doe thinges of our owne, that are prophane or wicked: And becauſe the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God are morall, the equity of this commaundement belongeth vnto vs. In deed there was ſome thinge peculiar to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in reſpect of the ceremonie, and the day: But there is yet a day to be kept, becauſe intermiſſions from the trauailes of this life, are neceſſarie both for the ſoule and bodye: That both the one and the other may be prouided for, the Soule to be fedde, and the bodye to reſt, our ſelues and our Seruanntes,
<pb facs="tcp:184043:16"/> (yea our very cattle) are to be fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this behalfe, becauſe of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne conſecration to God. And therefore the king of <hi>Niniuie,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that that ſolemne Faſt ſhoulde be extended euen to the Oxe within the ſtaule, and to the Horſe in the ſtable, and to euery beaſt of the field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith <hi>I ſay) is the man that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 56. 2.</note> 
               <hi>doth this, and the Sonne of that man that layeth hold of this, taking heed, that be defile not my Sabboth, and keeping his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 58. 13.</note> 
               <hi>handes that they doe no euyll: If thou shalt turne thy foote from my Sabboth, doe not that thou delightest in, on my holy day: If thou shalt call it, thy delight holy to Iehouah and honorable, and shall honour it, not in exerciſing thine owne wayes, not in performing that which thou delyghtest in, not in ſpeaking a vayn word, then I wyl aduaunce thee, deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Lord, vppon the hygh places of the Earth: and thou shalt enioy the poſſeſſion of Iacob thy father, becauſe the mouth of the Lorde ſpeaketh it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So God ſpeaketh by the Prophet<note place="margin">Iere. 17. 21.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:184043:16"/> 
               <hi>Ieremy</hi> alſo: <hi>Take beede vnto your ſelues and bear not burdens vppon the Sabboth day, neyther bring thoſe thinges into the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 20. 20.</note> 
               <hi>gates of Ieruſalem. &amp;c.</hi> The Prophets are very vehemente in this behalfe: &amp; therefore our ſinne ſtandeth at the dore, that haue made no regarde of theſe thinges. For we do worſe then beare burdens.</p>
            <p>Not onely oure carriers Poſte vppe and downe, but men trauaile all moſte with oute conſcience in euerye quarter, yea wee doe thinges that are naught, and therefore the wrath of God, muſt néedes be powred out againſt vs.</p>
            <p>And yet God hath ſhewed vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe fewe yeeres, many fearfull ſignes and tokens of his heauye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſpleaſure, and one iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente dothe euen ouertake another, and yet nothing can mooue vs.</p>
            <p>Hee hathe ſpoken to vs from Heauen by Comettes, Ecclypſes, and fiery impreſſions, he hath ſet Starres in vnwoonted places, &amp; ſent vpon the world, ſtrange tempeſts. He
<pb facs="tcp:184043:17"/> hath rumbled in the howels of the earth farre and wyde: and hath loſed the depeſt and ſtrongeſt foundations. The earthe hath quaked at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the very creature hath ſled from before his face. He hath ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the windowes of heauen, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the earth with his diſpleaſure. He hath made bare the rootes of the corne, and fedde the foules with our nouriſhment. Hee hath ſent out the peſtilence, and burning fire from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his feete, that they might waſt and deuoure the inhabitauntes of the earth. Many men haue receiued ſhort ſummons, to appeare before him, &amp; to render account of their doinges. <hi>They haue perished</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>by the blast of his mouth, and by the breath of his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 4. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>nostrils they are conſumed. By the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Lyon, and by the voyce of the fierce Lyon. and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the teeth of the Lyons whelpes, they are ground to pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding all theſe Iudgementes and manye more, that I can not reckon vp,
<pb facs="tcp:184043:17"/> who turneth to the Lord, who leaueth his wickednes: and forſaketh the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of fooles? Who is wiſe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the plagues at home and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that are abroade, that he may be prepared to a better Kingdome? Who looketh to the kéepinge of the <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> and conſidereth this feareful example, fallen out amongſt vs?</p>
            <p>But that it may be remembred the better to doo vs good, that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harmes of other, we may make our profite I will ſet it downe as plainly as I can, and as truely as can be gathered from the examination of thoſe ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon euidenſes, that haue fallen out: waying ſome circumſtances that ſhall teach thée, that it was not the worke of any man, but the finger euen of God himſelfe, to warne vs to turne and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially from theſe ſinnes that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in that behalfe, for prophaning of the <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> which are too horrible</p>
            <p>You ſhall vnderſtande therefore (deare Chriſtians) that vpon the laſte Lordes day being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirtéen day of the firſt moneth, that cruell and lothſome
<pb facs="tcp:184043:18"/> exerciſe of bayting Beares being kept at <hi>Parriſgarden,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after none, in the time of common prayers, and when many other exerciſes of Religion, both of Preaching and Catechizinge were had in ſundrie places of the Cittie, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Preachers hauing not longe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo cried out againſte ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanatious: yet (the more pittie) there reſorted thether a greate company of people of all ſortes and conditiones, that the like nomber, in euery reſpecte (as they ſay) had not béene ſéene there a long time before.</p>
            <p>Being thus vngodlilie aſſembled, to ſo vnholy a ſpectacle and ſpecially conſidering the time: the yearde, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and Galleries beinge full fraught, being nowe amiddeſt their io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, when the <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Beare,</hi> were in their cheefeſt battell. Loe the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand of God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. This Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie that was double, and compaſſed the yarde round about, was ſo ſhaken at the foundation, that it fell flat to the ground, without poſte or peece, that was left ſtanding, ſo high as the ſtake
<pb facs="tcp:184043:18"/> whereunto the <hi>Beare</hi> was tyed.</p>
            <p>Although ſome will ſay (&amp; it may be truly) that it was very olde and rotten and that therefore a greater waight of people, beinge planted vpon it then was wont: that it was no maruell that it failed: and woulde make it but a light matter. Yet ſurelie if this be conſidered, that no one péece of poſte, borde or ſtocke was left ſtandinge; though wee vrge it net as a miracle, yet it muſt néeds be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered as an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>traordinary iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, both for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhment of theſe preſent propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Lords day, and alſo to in forme and warne others.</p>
            <p>In the fall of it, there weare ſlaine fiue men and two women, that are come to knowledge who they were and where they dwelled, to wit. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame Spencer</hi> a <hi>Felmonger,</hi> in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarke, William Cockram</hi> a Baker, dwellinge in <hi>Shordich, Iohn Burton</hi> Clarck, of S. <hi>Marie Wolmers</hi> in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bard streate. Mathevv Maſon,</hi> ſeruant with Maiſter <hi>Garlande,</hi> dwellinge in <hi>Southvvarke: Thomas Peace,</hi> ſeruant w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184043:19"/> 
               <hi>Robert Taſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Clerken vvell.</hi> The Maidons names <hi>Elice White</hi> ſeruaunt to a Purſmaker withoute <hi>Cripplegate:</hi> and <hi>Marie Hariſon,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Iohn Hariſon</hi> waterbearer, dwelling in <hi>Lombard ſtreet.</hi> Ther is to bée conſidered in the qualitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion of theſe perſons: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath thus laid alonge amiddeſt their vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to be an example vnto vs, how com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly theſe of ſuch ſorte are affected &amp; diſpoſed. For if theſe in the ſtate of poore men had feared God, and in the hearing of gods words had vppon ſuch ſhorte ſummons bene called to appere before God: yet had they lefte an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted teſtimonie, of their religion and pietie vnto others. And therefore I doo exhorte all men to take héede of ſuch follies. Let them learne alwaies to be prepared for death, ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death is ſo certaine, though no man know of the bower. If God haue ſette them in a meane ſtate, let them not followe rudeneſſe, nor hunte after ſuch vaine pleaſures, but ſéeke the beſt thinges, and thoſe that are moſt precious. Let
<pb facs="tcp:184043:19"/> them heard the comfortable worde of ſaluation that ſhall comforte them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pouertie, and other afflictions whereunto we are ſubiect in this life.</p>
            <p>And for ſeruauntes, let maiſters, ſee them better imployed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe dayes that are conſecreated to holy exerciſes that they may bee frée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their bloode, and lette ſeruauntes thinke it no bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to be reſtrained from ſuch vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: But alacke the worlde is nowe grown to that wickedneſſe, that the maiſters being prophane themſelues, the ſeruauntes are trained vp in all prophanation: yea ſeruaunts will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent afore hand, to haue their libertie vppon ſuch dayes to goe to the Deuill fréelie: &amp; thereof ſpring infinite corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions and ſinnes not to be named. If theſe ſeruaunts had had maiſters, that would haue called them to a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how they had ſpent that daye (as good maiſters oughte to haue done) and haue had an accompt what they hadde learned, they might haue had leſſe cauſe to ſorrow, becauſe they had performed good duties. But O you ſeruantes that
<pb facs="tcp:184043:20"/> feare God, returne from ſuch filthines Liue to God faithfully in your vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thinke it a great mercy that in peace, you may poſſeſſe ſuch a bountie. You ſe in theſe, fallen before you, an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample to make you ſéeke better things that you may walke as in the ſight of God faithfully to doo your duties: you ſée the vanitie of pleaſures: that our lyfe is but a puffe: to the end you may learne alwaies to bee in a readineſſe. You haue hearde that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his chylde alyue thether, caryed it home againe deade, which came not to paſſe by chaunce but by Goddes prouidence.</p>
            <p>Nowe beſide theſe that were thus killed outright, with the flat fal of the Galleries, ſtrangely wrunge in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at it were by God himſelfe, it cold not be but in ſuch confuſion, ther muſt néeds come greate hurt to many. Howe many carried away death, as it were in theyr boſomes, that dyed the ſame night, or ſome little tyme after, the Lord knoweth.</p>
            <p>But this is euydent, that ſome are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:184043:20"/> ſince dead, and namely a Pewterers wyfe, that dwelt in Limeſtréete, who being therefore wounded, is nowe dead, and diuers others. Of al the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude there, which muſte néedes be farre aboue a thouſande, it is thought by the iudgement of moſt people, that not the third perſonne eſcaped vnhurt: and by ſome that haue made ſearche, they eſteme that there were ſore hurt and maymed, one hundred and fyftye perſons, ſome theyr legs and armes broken, ſome theyr backes, theyr bodies being ſore bruſed, ſo that euery waye into the cittie from that time till towardes nine of the clocke and paſt: and ſpecially ouer <hi>London bridge,</hi> many were carried in Chayres, and ledde betwixte theyr friendes, and ſo brought home wyth ſorrowfull and heauy hartes.</p>
            <p>They ſay alſo that at the firſt, when the Scaffolde cracked (as it did once or twiſe) there was a crye of <hi>fire, fire,</hi> which ſet them in ſuch a maze as was wonderfull, ſo that as deſtitute of theyr wits, they ſtode ſtyll, and could
<pb facs="tcp:184043:21"/> make no ſhifte for them ſelues, til the Scaffold was ouerturned.</p>
            <p>But as in the execution of Gods iudgements, we ſhall often marke the miraculous prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; mercy of God towardes many, euen ſo fell it out with diuers of theſe, that when as they had iuſtly deſerued not onely to be hurt and wounded, but euen to be killed, yet God as a moſte mercifull Corrector rather ſéemed to haue ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a rodde towardes them., then to haue touched them. For amongſt the reſt it is credibly reported that thore was one Woman; that being in the Gallery, threwe downe her childe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her, &amp; leaped after her ſelfe: &amp; yet thankes be to God neyther of both had any maner of hurt, ſo was it with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others. But it ſhould appeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they were moſt hurte and in dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, which ſtoode vnder the Galleries on the grounde, vpon whom both the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghte of Tymbre and people fell. And ſure it was a miraculous worke of God, that any one of thoſe ſhould haue eſcaped.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:21"/>
            <p>But here alſo God ſhewed his power for one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling downe into a hole, it pleaſed God that it was the meane of his deliuerance, ſo as al things that ſel vpon him did not touch him, and by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was preſerued, whereas two of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were ſlaine of ech ſide of him.</p>
            <p>Nowe what wee haue to learne of theſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſufficiently hath bene touched before, and therefore for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: A beſéeche all Maieſtrates by the mercies of God in Ieſus Chriſt, that by this occaſion, they take good héede to looke to the people committed to their charge, that they take order eſpecially on the <hi>Sabaoth</hi> dayes that no <hi>Citizin</hi> or <hi>Citizins</hi> ſeruantes, haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to repayre vnto any of thoſe abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed places, that albeit the place be without the Citie, &amp; by that meanes, they haue not to deale with them, yet that they keepe their <hi>Beares</hi> out, and their ſtraggling <hi>Wantons</hi> in, that they may be better occupyed. And as they haue with good commendation ſo far preuailed, that vppon <hi>Sabaoth</hi> dayes theſe Heathniſh <hi>Enterludes</hi> and <hi>Plaies</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184043:22"/> are baniſhed, ſo it will pleaſe them to followe the matter ſtill, that they may be vtterlye rid and taken away. For ſurely it is to be feared, beſides the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction both of bodye and ſoule, that many are brought vnto, by frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Theater,</hi> the <hi>Curtin</hi> and ſuch like, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one day thoſe places wyl like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bée caſt downe by God himſelfe, &amp; with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a huge heape of ſuch contemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, &amp; prophane perſons vtterly kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; ſpoylod in their bodies. God hath giuen them as I haue heard manye faire warnings already.</p>
            <p>And as I praye Maieſtrates, ſo I béeſéeche Miniſters, my faithfull bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they performe this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woorke that God hath committed vnto them, that they call vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more earneſtly to kéepe the Lords <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> and that they employ themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in teaching, exhortation, and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, in Catechizing and trayning vp their people and youth, that they may know to deteſt ſuch corruptions: that being occupyed in ſuch holy exerciſes, they may be their crowne whom they
<pb facs="tcp:184043:22"/> ſhall winne to Chriſt and to this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>And laſtly I beſéeche you my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren all, of what eſtate or condition ſo euer you be: Faynt not in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie courſe of the Goſpell ſo freely and in ſo great mercye offered vnto you. Loue the aſſemblies of Gods Saints, that you may féele the hope and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of a better lyfe. Be aſhamed to followe vanities, which when you haue fedde your ſelues with as full as you can, can worke nothing in you but lothſomnes, vexation, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of ſpirite. Pleaſures are like vnto ſwéete poyſons, when the ſwéetenes is paſt, they worke tortures &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ts. Kéepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords <hi>Sabaothes.</hi> If you be Maiſters be patternes vnto your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes of diligence in hearing, and of true godlines, in putting holy doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in practiſe. If you be ſeruauntes and youth, learne in the dayes of your youth, before age and death come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you, that there is no felicitie but in the faith of Chriſt, there is no fayth wythout the miniſterye of the word,
<pb facs="tcp:184043:23"/> there is no miniſtery of the worde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe giftes be giuen vnto men of God, and they be reared, vp to teach you, and to lead you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes of God, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when theſe ordinarie meanes are neglected, dyſpiſed, and reſiſted, then we can haue no certainty or comfort of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord Ieſus who by his death and paſſion, reſurrection and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion into heauen, wrought full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his Father for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſaluation, gyue vs fayth and ſanctifie vs throughout, both bodies and ſoules: that we ſeruing him in a ſpirituall ſeruice in both, may féele it to be our greateſt happineſſe: may diſpiſe this vaine and totring world, may deteſt all vanities, and ſpecially accurſſed prophanations: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing faith and a good conſcience, may walke on with good courage in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of that euerlaſting inheritance which he hath ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dearely purchaſed for vs.</p>
            <closer>Amen.
<dateline>
                  <date>Ianuary. 17. 1583.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>I, F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184043:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
